Finding Aid for Integrated Premedical-Medical Program (University of Michigan) records, 1972-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Integrated Premedical-Medical Program (University of Michigan) records 1972-2002
University of Michigan. Integrated Premedical-Medical Program.
9620 Bimu C26 2
The Integrated Premedical-Medical Program, commonly called Inteflex, combined undergraduate and medical school education into one specialized curriculum program at the University of Michigan. Inteflex was conceived to allow an integrated, flexible program through a liberal arts education offered by the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts while also obtaining a medical degree through the Medical School. Inteflex began as a six-year program in 1971, expanded to seven years in 1982, and again to eight years in 1994. The Inteflex program accepted its last entering group of students in 1998.
7 linear feet
7 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 8377 ) was initially received from the unit in 1995. Additional accessions were added between 2000 and 2002
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Integrated Premedical-Medical Program records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy.
The Integrated Premedical-Medical Program record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- removed to vault
Inteflex, or the Integrated Premedical-Medical Program, began as an alternative to the traditional path of obtaining a medical degree: four years of premedical education focusing on the sciences and matriculation to medical school. Inteflex combined and accelerated these into one program. Inteflex aimed to produce a more caring and humane, rather than what was seen as a disease-oriented, physician. One of the original pushes to start the program was a national concern over a shortage of doctors. There was also a widely held perception that doctors were not overly compassionate. Due to these reasons, there was ample funding to start a program that would focus on creating humane doctors at an accelerated rate. It was decided to test the theory that an education based on the arts, social sciences, and ethics would produce a more caring doctor.
Inteflex distinguished itself by becoming an exclusive program offering openings for a limited number of LS&A students, 50 or fewer per year. Although acceptance to the program and the course-load was intense, "flexies" had a supportive atmosphere. Many of the students lived together in East Quad, a move that staff hoped would foster cooperation rather than competition. Inteflex also had specialized premedical counselors to help with academic or personal issues. Students also did not have to compete for entrance into medical school since they were guaranteed entrance with their Inteflex status.
Classes in the Inteflex program included a combination of standard LS&A courses and smaller classes only for Inteflex students. The program attempted to reduce the redundancy between premedical preparation and medical school while offering an introduction to the arts and social sciences. The original six-year program contained 24 months of concentrated undergraduate education, two years of basic medical sciences in small Inteflex classes, and two years of clinical clerkship with standard medical students.
One of the key Inteflex courses was Introduction to Patient Care, or the "preceptorship." This was a summer course that featured one-on-one work in a medical setting. The student was placed with a mentor doctor and worked along with him or her for two months. This took place the first summer at the university, exposing the students to patient care early in their medical training.
Since the program began as an experiment, the program was constantly being evaluated. Students were questioned, tested, and evaluated with regularity. The curriculum changed with the results of the studies. Inteflex was also continually making adjustments to conform to curriculum changes and standards set by the Medical School and LS&A. Inteflex leader made several adjustments to courses, requirements, length of study, and admissions over the years.
The program became a total of seven years in 1982. The undergraduate portion lengthened to three years. Inteflex students studied basic sciences with standard medical students, however they used different schedules. Yearly class size also decreased from fifty incoming students to forty. These adjustments were made due to a number of factors. The intense six year program made it difficult for students to finish their requirements within the required time span. LS&A required foreign language proficiency. It was often difficult for "flexies" to meet this requirement without previous instruction or advanced placement in high school. The initial national fervor to educate more doctors also declined. Funding for Inteflex also lessened at this time.
Inteflex expanded program length again in 1994 following massive curriculum changes within the Medical School the previous year. The new medical curriculum was too different to accommodate the former Inteflex structure and as a result, it became an eight year program. The undergraduate portion became four years long. Admissions were lowered again, from 40 to 35 incoming students per year. Also, Inteflex students were now required to pass the MCAT medical school examination and have a combined MCAT/GPA score of a certain level before entrance into the Medical School. This was a first for the program since previously students, once admitted into Inteflex, moved right into Medical School without separate applications, assessment, or testing. This move was initiated by the Medical School after finding that Inteflex students generally had more difficulty in Medical School than students taking the standard path. At this time, Inteflex changed focus slightly to accommodate and support more minorities and students from rural areas. Attention was given to producing primary care physicians, a continuation of the hope for more compassionate doctors. The program now also allowed students a non-M.D. degree option.
The program underwent close scrutiny in 1997. Reviewers included the Medical School, LS&A, and Inteflex faculty as well as Inteflex students, counselors, alumni, and staff. After much consideration, it was determined that Inteflex was no longer making an enduring contribution to either LS&A or the Medical School. The review committee decided that the curriculum was no longer innovative, the community was too stifling for the "real world" of medical school, and that Inteflex students were generally not academically better than regular medical students. Even though it was studied thoroughly, there was no final way of determining if the Inteflex program, with its small classes, individualized attention and focus on humanities, created a more compassionate doctor than students going through a traditional path. If they were using the family practice doctor as a resulting factor, then this did not prove to be the case. Most doctors who were "flexies" specialized in a particular branch as did most traditional students. The program accepted the last entering class in 1998, and Inteflex offices closed in 2002. The last group of "flexies" was scheduled to graduate Medical School in 2006.
The Integrated Premedical-Medical Program (Inteflex) Records are divided into six series: Administrative, Committees, Curricula, Reports, Students, and Visual Materials. An earlier two linear foot collection came to the library in 1996. Due to the size of the accessions following the program's discontinuance, the older records were absorbed to make one holistic record group. Yearly classes are known by several names throughout the papers. The two most commonly used classifications are by the year the class entered Inteflex and also by the year of graduation from the Medical School. Classes may also be known by their status in the program, such as I4 meaning the student is in the fourth year of Inteflex. To create the least confusion possible, classes within the finding aid are filed under the Medical School graduation year.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Integrated Premedical-Medical Program.; Medicine--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Premedical education.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative 1972-2000
  The Administrative series, 1972-2000 (1.0 linear feet), comprises materials used to manage and operate the Inteflex program. Included is a large volume of chronological correspondence sent out by the Inteflex administrative office including letters to prospective, current, and former students, other units, and people outside of the university. These files show the history and yearly activities of the staff. The series also contains collected data, director correspondence, office procedure manuals, and faculty retreat records.
  - Academic Calendars 1984-1995 (Box 1)
  - Admissions Data 1975-1993 (Box 1)
  - Donald R. Brown Vita 1993 (Box 1)
  - Budget 1992-1998 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Administrative 1973-1993 (Box 1)
    - Course Related 1973-1992 (Box 1)
    - Director 1980-1998 (Box 1)
    - General to Students 1972-1990 (Box 1)
    - Memos
      - 1975-1978 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1988 (Box 1)
    - Office
      - 1988 (Box 1)
      - 1994 (Box 1)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 1)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 1)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 1)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Counseling 1973-1999 (Box 1)
  - Dean 1993 (Box 1)
  - Inteflex Governance 1972-1994 (Box 1)
  - Inteflex Research 1977-1995 (Box 1)
  - Inteflex/LS&A Procedural/General Materials 1973-1992 (Box 1)
  - Office Instruction Manual (The Lifesaver), undated (Box 1)
  - Office Schedules 1975-1997 (Box 1)
  - Outreach 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Organizational Chart 1993 (Box 1)
  - Relocation
    - Alice Lloyd 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - East Quad 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Retreat
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1984 (Box 1)
    - 1994 (Box 1)
  - Shipman Weekend 1997 (Box 1)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Student Attrition/Withdrawal 1977-1986 (Box 1)
  - Student Tracking Statistics circa 1980-1992 (Box 1)
- Committees 1973-2000
  The series Committees, 1973-2000 (1.1 linear feet), documents the interdisciplinary nature of the Inteflex Program and its evolution. The Admissions Committee records the changing student demographics over time. The Inteflex Review Committee, formed of Inteflex, Medical School, and LS&A faculty, examined the structure and progress of the Inteflex Program in 1993 and 1997. The progress is shown through correspondence, questionnaires, and reports. The Participating Faculty minutes report faculty and student solutions to internal Inteflex problems. The Policy Committee minutes contain high-level administration discussions about Inteflex policy. This subseries seems to continue under the name Steering Committee beginning in the 1990s. It is a particularly rich source of information on the Inteflex program evaluation containing detailed minutes, reports, and some correspondence.
  - Academic Review Board 1995
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2070 ]
  - Admissions Committee
    - Admissions Forms 1982-1995 (Box 1)
    - Manual 1993 (Box 1)
    - Minutes
      - 1973-1987 (Box 1)
      - 1988-1993 (Box 1)
      - 1994-1999 (Box 1)
  - Conference on Ethics, Humanism, and Medicine 1979-1994 (Box 2)
  - Inteflex Review Committee
    - 1993 Review, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - 1997 Review
      - Correspondence 1996-1997 (Box 2)
      - Review Committee Questions 1997 (Box 2)
      - Report 1997 (Box 2)
      - Survey Questionnaires
        - Alumni 1997 (Box 2)
        - Counselors 1997 (Box 2)
        - Faculty 1997 (Box 2)
        - Steering Committee 1997 (Box 2)
        - Students 1997 (Box 2)
  - Participating Faculty Committee Minutes
    - 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
  - Policy Committee Minutes
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1992 (Box 2)
  - Steering Committee Minutes
    - 1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
    - 1997
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2072 ]
    - 1998 (Box 3)
    - 1999 (Box 3)
    - 1999
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2074 ]
    - 2000
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2075 ]
- Curricula 1972-1999
  The Curricula series, 1972-1999 (2.2 linear feet), includes information regarding the numerous learning opportunities of the Inteflex student. The largest subseries is Courses. This includes syllabi and descriptions of Inteflex classes as well as courses offered through LS&A. A large amount of records are devoted to the Inteflex course "Introduction to Patient Care" and include student/doctor assignments, schedules, and course materials. The curricula series also includes class evaluations by students, requirements for the Inteflex program and concentrations, and grading policies.
  - Concentrations/Dual Programs
    - Business Program 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Concentration Proposal 1995 (Box 3)
    - School of Public Health Program 1996-1997 (Box 3)
  - Courses
    - Approvals 1973-1987 (Box 3)
    - Changes 1976-1993 (Box 3)
    - Course Proposals 1989-1996 (Box 3)
    - Inteflex
      - Freshmen Seminar
        - Correspondence 1972-1991 (Box 3)
        - Course Rosters 1979-1989 (Box 3)
        - Descriptions
          - IFX 100
            - 1977-1989 (Box 3)
            - 1990-1998 (Box 3)
          - IFX 101 1978-1998 (Box 3)
          - IFX 102/103 1995 (Box 3)
      - IFX 201/PSY 380: Nature of Illness 1975-1995 (Box 3)
      - IFX 210: Introduction to Patient Care
        - Calendar/Schedule (Box 3)
        - Course Handouts 1975-1994 (Box 3)
        - Cumulative Match List of Preceptor Doctors 1983-1994 (Box 3)
        - Preceptorship Materials 1975-1986 (Box 3)
        - Recruitment 1983-1995 (Box 3)
        - Tri-University Participation (University of Michigan, Michigan State University, Wayne State University) 1991 (Box 3)
        - Yearly Course Information and Rosters 1973-1997, 23 folders (Box 3)
      - IFX 211: Introduction to Health Care 1995-1999 (Box 4)
      - IFX 212: Introduction to Health Care: The Social Sciences 1995-1996 (Box 4)
      - IFX 301: The Changing Political Economy of Health and Disease 1990-1993 (Box 4)
      - IFX 401: Human Sexuality 1985-1998 (Box 4)
      - IFX 500: Introduction to Clinical Sciences 1982 (Box 4)
      - IFX 505: Human Genetics 1981 (Box 4)
      - IFX 506/507: Anatomy 1981-1992 (Box 4)
      - IFX 560/561: Physiology 1981 (Box 4)
      - IFX 630/640/650: Human Illness undated (Box 4)
    - Inter-Departmental Courses
      - Anatomy 1977 (Box 4)
      - Biology 1997 (Box 4)
      - Chemistry 1979-1997 (Box 4)
      - Clinical Studies 1981-1991 (Box 4)
      - Philosophy 1985-1996 (Box 4)
      - Physics 1972-1988 (Box 4)
      - Psychology 1979-1996 (Box 4)
      - Social Science undated (Box 4)
      - Statistics 1993 (Box 4)
    - Evaluations by Students
      - IFX 210: Introduction to Patient Care undated (Box 4)
      - Phase I, Year I 1972-1990 (Box 4)
      - Phase I, Year I and II 1972-1977 (Box 4)
      - Phase I, Year II 1973-1990 (Box 4)
      - Phase II, Year III 1975-1989 (Box 4)
      - Phase II, Year IV 1972-1988 (Box 5)
      - Review 1974-1996 (Box 5)
    - Semester Schedules 1980-1992 (Box 5)
  - Curricula
    - Schedules 1973-1996 (Box 5)
    - Changes
      - 1980-1985 (Box 5)
      - 1987-1989 (Box 5)
      - 1992-1994 (Box 5)
      - 1997 (Box 5)
  - Grading Policy 1981-1995 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Education Trust 1997 (Box 5)
  - Other Experiences
    - Lancaster Program (Study Abroad) 1996-1997 (Box 5)
    - Off-Campus Experiences 1996 (Box 5)
  - Program Requirements
    - English Composition Board 1982-1995 (Box 5)
    - Honors Program 1985-1994 (Box 5)
    - Prematriculation Program 1996 (Box 5)
- Reports 1972-1999
  The series Reports, 1972-1999 (1.0 linear feet) compiles the multitude of studies conducted by the Inteflex, LS&A, and Medical School faculty and committees. Many of the reports are student interview results describing their experiences, achievements, and satisfaction of the program. Some classes were interviewed at several stages within their academic careers. The results are arranged by the students' graduation year for clarity and consistency purposes. Many reports from the later years are in electronic format.
  - 1978 Postgraduate Year Six Questionnaire, 1978 Medical School Graduating Class, 1986 (Box 5)
  - 1979
    - 1979 Medical School Graduating Class, Postgraduate Year Six Questionnaire (Box 5)
    - Academic and Career Development Within the LS&A Control Group (1972-1975) (Box 5)
    - Attrition Patterns in the Inteflex Program (Box 5)
    - Career Development in Inteflex Students (Box 5)
    - Development of Inteflex Students (1972-1977) and a Comparison of Their Personal and Professional Attitudes to Those of Standard Medical Students (Box 5)
    - Faculty Members' Assessments of the Inteflex Program (Box 5)
    - Inteflex Admissions Report: Descriptive Data for Qualified Applicants 1972-1977 (Box 5)
    - Inteflex Funding (Box 5)
    - Liberal Arts in the Inteflex Program (Box 5)
    - Student Achievement Within the Inteflex Program During the First Six Years of the Program (1972-1978) (Box 5)
    - Student Satisfaction with the Inteflex Program: Issues and Perceptions (Box 5)
  - 1980
    - [Class of 1980 Tenth-Year Postgraduate Study], 1991 (Box 5)
    - Report of Evaluative Data Regarding the Inteflex Program (Box 5)
  - 1981
    - Report of Evaluative Data Regarding the Inteflex Program (Box 5)
  - 1982
    - Class of 1982 Report to Participants [Sixth-Year Postgraduate Study] (Box 5)
    - Inteflex Evaluation and Future Options of the Program (Box 5)
  - 1983
    - 1983 Medical School Graduating Class: Postgraduate Year Two Questionnaire, 1986 (Box 5)
    - [Class of 1983 Sixth-Year Postgraduate Study] Report to Participants, 1990 (Box 5)
    - Combined Premedical-Medical Programs: Program Structures and Student Outcomes at Four Universities (Box 5)
    - Integrating and Accelerating Medical Education: The Combined Baccalaureate-M.D. Programs at Boston University, the City College of New York, the University of Michigan, and the University of Missouri-Kansas City, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1984
    - 1984 Medical School Graduating Class: Postgraduate Year Two Questionnaire, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Task Force on Medical Education (Box 5)
  - 1985
    - [Class of 1985]: Integrated Premedical-Medical Program Sixth-Year Interview Summary 1979 Entering Class (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1985]: Standard Medical School Program Fourth-Year Interview Summary 1981 Entering Class (Box 6)
    - Program Evaluation by Standard Medical Students 1976-1980 Entering Class (Box 6)
    - Workshop on the Liberal Arts (Box 6)
  - 1986
    - [Class of 1986]: Integrated Premedical-Medical Six-Year Interview Summary 1980 Entering Class (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1986 Second-Year Postgraduate Study] Report to Participants, 1989 (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1986]: Standard Medical School Program Fourth-Year Interview Summary 1982 Entering Class (Box 6)
  - 1987
    - [Class of 1987 Second-Year Postgraduate Study] Report to Participants, 1991 (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1987]: Standard Medical School Program Fourth-Year Interview Summary 1983 Entering Class (Box 6)
  - 1988 [Class of 1988]: 1984 Standard Medical Students Interview Summary (electronic file on disc 1 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
  - 1989
    - [Class of 1989]: 1985 Standard Medical Students Interview Summary (electronic file on disc 5 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1989]: Seventh Year Inteflex Interview Summary Report, 1982-A Entering Class (electronic file on disc 3 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
  - 1990
    - [Class of 1990]: Inteflex Fifth Year Interview Summary 1983 Entering Class (electronic file on disc 1 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1990]: Integrated Pre-Medical and Medical Seventh-Year Interview Summary 1983 Entering Class (electronic file on disc 5 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1990]: Standard Medical Students Interview Summary (electronic file on disc 2 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
  - 1991
    - [Class of 1991]: Fourth-Year Standard Medical Students 1987 Entering Class (electronic file on disc 4 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1991]: Nineties in 1984 Entering Inteflex Class Interviews (electronic file on disc 5 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1991]: Nineties in the M/4 Interview, [Entering] Class of 1987 (electronic file on disc 2 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1991]: Seventh Year Inteflex Interview Summary Report 1984 Entering Class (electronic file on disc 4 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
  - 1992
    - New Responses 1988 [Entering Medical School] Class (electronic file on disc 2 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1992]: Nineties in the Fifth Year Inteflex Interviews, Entering Class 1985 (electronic file on disc 1 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1992]: Nineties in the M/4 Interview, [Entering] Class of 1988 (electronic file on disc 3 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1992]: Nineties in the 7th Year Interview 1985 Entering Class (electronic file on disc 3 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1992]: Third-Year Inteflex Interview Summary 1985 Entering Class (electronic file on disc 1 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - Evaluative Reports on the Inteflex Program (Box 6)
  - 1993
    - [Class of 1993]: Fifth Year Inteflex Interview Summary Report 1986 Entering Class (electronic file on disc 4 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1993]: Nineties in the 7th Year Interview 1986 Entering Class (electronic file on disc 4 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
    - Final Report to the Dean of LS&A from the Committee to Review the LS&A Component of the Inteflex Program (Box 6)
  - 1994/1995 Building Undergraduate Academic Communities and Delivering Student Support Services (Box 6)
  - 1995
    - Academic Performance Analyses: Inteflex Students I4/M1 Year 1988-1995 (Box 6)
    - [Class of 1995]: I-5 New Responses 1988 [Entering] Class (electronic file on disc 2 located at the end of the series) (Box 6)
  - 1996
    - Summary Report on the LS&A Component of Inteflex (Box 6)
    - Self-Study: LS&A Component -- Inteflex Program (Box 6)
  - 1997
    - Academic Performance Analysis: Inteflex Students (With Comparative Data from Standard Classes) (Box 6)
    - Final Report: Inteflex Internal Review Committee (Box 6)
  - 1999 Report of the Committee to Review Undergraduate Premedical Education (Box 6)
  - Electronic Files Stored on Discs (Box 6)
- Student Life 1972-2000
  The Student Life series, 1972-2000 (0.6 linear feet) reveals some aspects of life as an Inteflex student as well as life as a medical student. The series includes class rosters and alumni lists, activities, and relevant topical files such as housing and tutoring. The award subseries describes special achievements by students and includes correspondence and award background information. The Student Representatives subseries documents involvement with Inteflex committees and community service. The Student Council Agendas and Minutes are particularly dense with student involvement.
  - Activities 1998 (Box 6)
  - Alumni Lists 1982-1995 (Box 6)
  - Awards
    - Michael Archibald Award 1986-2000, 1 folders
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2075 ]